Hey guys, Coach Brett Conturus here.
This is going to be a video to explain
why if you're trying to maximize
athletic potential, why you would want
to do heavy resistance training and
explosive training. So, here I've got a
graph of a force velocity curve. Okay?
On the y ais is velocity measured is in
in meters/s and on the x axis here is
force measured in newtons. So, this
shows you I've got two points on the
spectrum here. I've got this dot and
this dot. This example would be like a
vertical jump. Okay, here you've got a
vertical jump and here you've got this
example would be like a squat. Okay,
that's your heavy squat. So, if if you
do a vertical jump, you don't you don't
have you're force isn't quite as high
because um you know it's not a lot of
force. You're just using body mass, but
your velocity is higher on the spectrum.
Whereas a squat, you're using heavier
weight. you're going to have more force,
but you're not doing it as explosive.
Your velocity won't be as high. So, here
are two different points on your force
velocity curve. And when you undertake,
so here's your baseline strength. These
different examples will be, you know,
hypothetical scenarios of like say eight
weeks of heavy resistance training would
be in the green, eight weeks of
um explosive training in the red, and
then blue would be combined training.
I'll explain this more in a second. So,
let's say I take a normal person, a
normal athlete, and I do eight weeks of
really heavy, you know, heavy resistance
training, squats and deadlifts and hip
thrust and bench press and stuff like
that. Okay, what this is going to do is
going to shift the whole curve, but it's
going to shift the curve more on the
force side of things, but it will help
increase their explosive force as well.
So, here's what the new curve looks
like.
Okay. So, as you can see here, it
extends this curve out a little bit on
the velocity side of of the equation and
more so on the force side of the
equation. So, now I've got, you know,
here's my new squat. I'm a lot more I um
I can at the same force I can now
produce it at more velocities but now I
can also squat heavier but it shifts the
whole curve over. Okay, my vertical jump
went up too. You know, now the new point
is right there. However,
if let's say I do eight weeks of
explosive training, okay, this doesn't
affect the force side quite as much.
but it affects the velocity side of the
curve more. And so, yeah, it did help my
squat come up a little, but it helped my
vertical jump tremendously. So, now, you
know, my new vertical jump is up here,
you know, and my new squat is only here.
However, what this curve shows us, what
this graph shows us is that neither of
these are ideal just doing one method.
If you do combined training, so if you
did both of these methods, you would
take the best of both of these curves.
And so here you've got the red.
So here's my blue curve from combined
training. You've got the red.
follow it down until it meets the green
like that. So, as you can see, here's
your new curve.
And so, if you do combined heavy and
explosive training, now you have shifted
your entire curve to the right, you can
produce more force. You can produce more
absolute velocity, more absolute force.
But every point in the middle, every
combination of those has now increased.
You've got a more explosive athlete now.
And in a lot of sports, say for example
on an NFL football player, he needs to
be able to produce a lot of u force with
his own body weight, you know, a lot of
acceleration, a lot of explosive
strength just with his own body weight.
But he also has to be very strong
because he might have an opponent on him
and he's dragging an opponent. Um, so he
needs to be strong at every end of this
force velocity curve. And so this helps
illustrate why you would want to do both
heavy training and explosive training.